Guide to the New York State Teachers Association Records 1915-1979
New York State Teachers Association Records
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation and Archives, Cornell University Library
New York State Teachers Association Records, 1915-1979
5293
New York State Teachers Association (NYSTA)
225.1 linear ft.
Records.
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation and Archives, Cornell University Library
ORGANIZATIONAL HISTORY
Among NYSTA's efforts on behalf of public education were the creation of the NYS Retirement System, the minimum salary law, the teachers' contract law, compulsory free education, state aid to local schools, teacher tenure laws and the creation of the New York State Department of Education.
COLLECTION DESCRIPTION
The Center is the official depository for the records of this organization which began its existence in 1845. The bulk of the records cover the period from 1950 through 1970. The collection includes minutes and files of the Board of Directors,23-1969; minutes and files of the House of Delegates, 1911970; the files of various officers; legislative files; historical files; and subject files.
SUBJECTS
Names:
American Association of University Professors; American Federation of Teachers; American Management Association; Associated Community College Facilities; Association of Assistant Principals; Association of Colleges and Universities of the State of New York; Business Teachers Association of New York State; Central School Boards Committee for Educational Research (N.Y.); Citizens' Committee for Children of New York.; City Teachers Association (New York, N.Y.); City University of New York. Legislative Conference; City-Wide Committee for Equal Retirement for New York City Teachers; Civil Service Employees Association (N.Y.); Classroom Teachers Association of New York State; Columbia University; Council of Chief State School Officers; Council on Educational Needs; Democratic Party (U.S.); Educational Conference Board; Fordham University; Hartwick College; Joint Legislative Committee on School Financing (N.Y.); Manhattan College; Nassau County Classroom Teachers Association; National Association of Secretaries of State Teachers Associations; National Council of State Education Associations; National Education Association of the United States; National Higher Education Staff Association; National School Public Relations; National Society of Professors; New York Association for Continuing Education; New York Congress of Teachers; New York (N.Y.). Board of Education.; New York Senate Professional Staff Association; New York (State). Board of Regents.; New York (State). Dept. of Education; New York (State). Legislature. Assembly.; New York (State). Legislature. Joint Committee on Industrial and Labor Conditions.; New York (State). Public Employment Relations Board.; New York (State). Temporary State Commission on Campus Unrest.; New York State Art Teachers Association; New York State Association for Childhood Education; New York State Association for Supervision and Curriculum Development; New York State Association of Elementary, Kindergarten and Nursery Education; New York State Association of Elementary School Principals; New York State Association of Public School Adult Educators; New York State Association of School District Administrators; New York State Association of Secondary School Administrators; New York State Association of Teachers of Mentally Handicapped; New York State Attendance Teachers Association; New York State Board of Cooperative Services; New York State Citizens Committee for Public Schools; New York State Congress of Parents and Teachers; New York State Council for the Social Studies; New York State Council of Administrators of Health, Physical Education and Recreation; New York State Council of School Superintendents; New York State Dental Hygiene Teachers Association; New York State Education Commission Association; New York State English Council; New York State Institution Educators Association; New York State Public Employees' Legislative Alliance; New York State Retired Teachers Association; New York State School Boards Association; New York State School Nurse Teachers Association; New York State School of Industrial and Labor Relations; New York State Teachers Association; New York State Teachers Retirement Board; Professional Staff Association; Republican Party (U.S.); Schenectady County Community College; Senate Professional Association (N.Y.); State University of New York; Teachers Union of the City of New York; United Federation of Teachers; United States. National Labor Relations Board.; United Teachers of New York; University of Michigan; University of New Haven; University of Rochester; Villa Maria College; Wayne State University; West Chester State College; World Confederation of Organizations of the Teaching Profession; Brown, Lorraine; Bush, Ronald; Carey, Sheridan; Cogen, Charles; Conroy, Helene; De Marco, Andrew; Doherty, Robert E. (Robert Emmett), 1923-; Eldred, Arvie; Encinio, Philip; Freeman, Ira; German, Robert; Goold, G. Howard; Granger, Robert; Harvey, John; Helmsby, Robert; Hobart, Thomas; Hopkins, Ned; Hurd, T. Norman; Kafka, Emanuel; Law, Kenneth; Macdonald, Bruce; Purcell, Edward; Stinnett, T. M., 1901-; Streiff, Dean; Walters, Marguerite; Weeks, Zoraida; White, Francis
Subjects:
Teachers' unions--New York (State)--Sources.
INFORMATION FOR USERS
Access Restrictions:
Access to the collections in the Kheel Center is restricted. Please contact a reference archivist for access to these materials.
RELATED MATERIALS
Related Collections:
5293 mf: New York State Teachers Association Guide to Records on Microfilm
SERIES LIST
Series I: Board of Directors Minutes 1923-69, 1923-1969
Sub-Series A: Minutes 1923-1968
Series II: House of Delegates, 1915-1969
Sub-Series A: Minutes 1915-70, 1915-1970
Sub-Series B: Resolution Committee Reports, 1950-69, 1950-1969
Sub-Series C: Contributions to Welfare Fund, 1929-47, 1929-1947
Sub-Series D: Tapes of 1969 House of Delegates, 1969
Series III: Executive Secretary's Files
Sub-Series A: Annual Reports, 1929-1971
Sub-Series B: Eldred Subject Files, 1953-1953, 1953
Sub-Series C: Goold Subject Files, 1950-1971, 1950-1971
Sub-Series D: White Subject Files
Series IV: Assistant Executive Secretary's Files
Sub-Series A: Kullman Subject Files
Series V: NYSTA
Sub-Series A: History, 1869-1969
Series VI: Communication and Legislation Files
Sub-Series A: Rose Subject Files, 1950-1968
Sub-Series B: Hopkins Subject Files, 1969-1972
Sub-Series C: News Clippings, 1970-1972
Series VII: Professional and Regional Services Files
Sub-Series A: Directors Files
Sub-Series B: General Files
Sub-Series C: Higher Education Files
Series VIII: Research Division
Sub-Series A.SSSPPP (Salary Survey), 1964-1970
Sub-Series B. Interview Studies of Select Districts., 1970
Series IX: New York State Teachers (NYSUT), 1972
CONTAINER LIST
- Series I: Board of Directors Minutes 1923-69, 1923-1969
  This series contains minute books which include not only the official minutes but agendas, correspondence, and reports related to the minutes. Meetings were generally held in February, March, May, August, September, December, and special meetings were occasionally held. A comprehensive subject index to these minute books (on index cards) is in boxes 19-20. An index is also included in the accession folder.
  - Sub-Series A: Minutes 1923-1968
    - May 1923-November 1939 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - December 1939-November 1945 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - December 1945-November 1948 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - December 1948- November 1950 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - December 1950-November 1951 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - December 1951-November 1952, 1951-1952 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - December 1952-November 1953, 1952-1953 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - December 1953-November 1955, 1953-1955 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - December 1955-November 1956, 1955-1956 (Box 2, Folder 1)
    - December 1956-November 1957, 1956-1957 (Box 2, Folder 2)
    - December 1957-November 1958, 1957-1958 (Box 2, Folder 2)
    - December 1958-September 1959, 1958-1959 (Box 2, Folder 3)
    - November 1959 (Box 2, Folder 4)
    - December 1959-November 1960, 1959-1960 (Box 2, Folder 5)
    - December 1960-November 1961, 1960-1961 (Box 3, Folder 1)
    - December 1961-November 1962, 1961-1962 (Box 3, Folder 2)
    - December 1962- May 1963, 1962-1963 (Box 3, Folder 3)
    - August 1963-November 1963 (Box 3, Folder 4)
    - December 1963-August 1964, 1963-1964 (Box 4, Folder 1)
    - September 1964-November 1964 (Box 4, Folder 2)
    - December 1964- September 1965, 1964-1965 (Box 4, Folder 3)
    - November 1965- March 1966, 1965-1966 (Box 4, Folder 4)
    - April 1966-August 1966 (Box 4, Folder 5)
    - September 1966 (Box 4, Folder 6)
    - November 1966-February 1967, 1966-1967 (Box 5, Folder 1)
    - March 1967-September 1967 (Box 5, Folder 2)
    - November 1967-May 1968, 1967-1968 (Box 5, Folder 3)
    - August 1968 (Box 5, Folder 4)
    - September 1968-November 1969, 1968-1969 (Box 6, Folder 1)
    - September 1969 and Special Meeting of October 1969 (Box 6, Folder 2)
    - December 1968-august 1969, 1968-1969 (Box 6, Folder 3)
    - Index (Box 6, Folder 4)
    - Index (Box 6, Folder 5)
- Series II: House of Delegates, 1915-1969
  - Sub-Series A: Minutes 1915-70, 1915-1970
    This series contains transcript minutes of the November annual meetings. The are arranged chronologically with banquet or speech transcripts following the minutes. Minutes for 1917 and 1922 are not included.
    - 1915-1924 (Box 7, Folder 1)
    - 1925-1927 (Box 7, Folder 2)
    - 1928-1931 (Box 7, Folder 3)
    - 1932-1936 (Box 8, Folder 1)
    - 1934-1939 (Box 8, Folder 2)
    - 1940-1943 (Box 8, Folder 3)
    - 1944-1947 (Box 9, Folder 1)
    - 1948-1949 (Box 9, Folder 2)
    - 1950-1953 (Box 9, Folder 3)
    - 1954-1956 (Box 10, Folder 1)
    - 1957-1958 (Box 10, Folder 2)
    - 1959-1960 (Box 10, Folder 3)
    - 1961-1962 (Box 11, Folder 4)
    - 1963-1964 (Box 11, Folder 5)
    - 1965-1966 (Box 11, Folder 6)
    - 1967 (Box 12, Folder 1)
    - 1968-69, 1968-1969 (Box 12, Folder 2)
    - 1970 (Box 12, Folder 3)
  - Sub-Series B: Resolution Committee Reports, 1950-69, 1950-1969
    Reports to the House of Delegates which contain the committees' analysis of resolutions being brought before the House. There are often supplementary reports. Arranged chronologically with supplementary reports included after the regular report.
    - Resolution Committee Reports, 1950-1969 (Box 12, Folder 4)
  - Sub-Series C: Contributions to Welfare Fund, 1929-47, 1929-1947
    This series contains the ledger books recording contributions for the NYSTA Welfare Fund. They are arranged chronologically.
    - Contributions to Welfare Fund, 1929-47, 1929-1947 (Box 13, Folder 1)
  - Sub-Series D: Tapes of 1969 House of Delegates, 1969
    This series contains tape recordings of the 1969 House of Delegates
    - Tapes of 1969 House of Delegates (Box 13, Folder 2)
- Series III: Executive Secretary's Files
  - Sub-Series A: Annual Reports, 1929-1971
    - Annual Reports 1929,52,54-55-[1958-71], 1929-1971 (Box 14, Folder 1)
      this series contains the annual reports to the membership concerning NYSTA's accomplishments for the previous ear and the objectives of the coming year. Often, the report contains the financial statements of the accountant and the finance Committee, as well as the annual reports of the standing committees.
    - Annual Reports 1929,52,54-55-[1958-71], 1929-1971 (Box 14, Folder 2)
    - Annual Reports 1929,52,54-55-[1958-71], 1929-1971 (Box 14, Folder 3)
  - Sub-Series B: Eldred Subject Files, 1953-1953, 1953
    This series contains the files of Arvie Eldred, Executive Secretary of NYSTA from 1930-1951. Boxes 44-46 contain his files concerning the Executive committee (forerunner of the Board of Directors) meetings. The files contain memos, reports, and correspondence as well as minutes and materials distributed at the meetings. These files are arranged chronologically by year with general subject files first for that year followed by the meeting folders. Box 47 contains Eldred's files on the House of Delegate meetings. These are arranged chronologically with subject files following the meeting files. As with the Executive Committee files, these records are fragmentary. Box 48 contains miscellaneous subject and correspondence files, arranged chronologically and the alphabetical within a year.
    - Sub-Series a: Executive Committee
      - Minutes-1925-30, 1925-1930 (Box 14, Folder 4)
      - Meeting, February 21, 1935 (Box 14, Folder 5)
      - Minutes for Sept. 22, May 11, Feb. 21, 1935 (Box 14, Folder 6)
        Also general correspondence
      - Meeting, Feb 17, 1936 (Box 14, Folder 7)
      - Minutes for Feb. 7, 1936 and May 16, 1936 and information regarding the NYSTA retirement program (Box 14, Folder 8)
      - June5, 1936 meeting (Box 14, Folder 9)
      - General correspondence, 1938 (Box 14, Folder 10)
      - Sub-committee re: classroom teachers and general correspondence, 1939-41, 1939-1941 (Box 14, Folder 11)
      - Correspondence, 1940 (Box 14, Folder 12)
      - Correspondence notes, 1940 (Box 14, Folder 13)
      - Meeting, June 8, 1940 (Box 14, Folder 14)
      - Minutes, 1940 (Box 14, Folder 15)
      - Minutes, 1940 (Box 14, Folder 16)
      - Meeting, Sept. 14, 1940 (Box 14, Folder 17)
      - Meeting, May 17, 1941 (Box 14, Folder 18)
      - Minutes, Jan-Nov. 1941. (Box 14, Folder 19)
        Correspondence concerning regents exams and correspondence concerning Exec. Sec. Eldred's recommendations dealing with the amendment of the NYSTA constitution.
      - Sub-committee on Amendment to Constitution materials, 1941 (Box 14, Folder 20)
        Correspondence and memos from Arvie Eldred concerning the drafting and content of the proposed amendments, 1941.
      - report on Public Relations, 1941 (Box 14, Folder 21)
      - Correspondence and notes, 1942-43, 1942-1943 (Box 14, Folder 22)
      - Correspondence from Arvie Eldred (Exec. Sec.), 1943 (Box 14, Folder 23)
        Between Emily Trabell concerning tenure bills and their legislative problems. Also minutes, 1943.
      - Correspondence, 1943 (Box 14, Folder 24)
        re: tenures in rural schools; aid to union free schools. Also minutes, 1943.
      - Correspondence, 1944 (Box 15, Folder 1)
      - Meetings correspondence, Jan.-May 1945 (Box 15, Folder 2)
      - Meetings correspondence, June-Dec. 1945 (Box 15, Folder 3)
      - Statement (Box 15, Folder 4)
        re: expansion of the services of Exec. Sec. to membership
      - NEA Presidency, 1946 (Box 15, Folder 5)
      - General Correspondence, 1946 (Box 15, Folder 6)
      - Meetings Correspondence, Jan.-Feb. 1946 (Box 15, Folder 7)
      - Meetings Correspondence, March-April 1946 (Box 15, Folder 8)
      - Meetings Correspondence May-Nov. 1946 (Box 15, Folder 9)
      - Planning committee, 1947 (Box 15, Folder 10)
      - Public Relations Committee, 1947 (Box 15, Folder 11)
      - Teacher Placement, 1947-1949 (Box 15, Folder 12)
        Report of sub-committee and other reports, 1947-1949
      - Meetings, Dec. 1946- Jan. 1947, 1946-1947 (Box 15, Folder 13)
      - Meetings, Jan. 31, 1947 (Box 15, Folder 14)
      - Correspondence, June 1948 (Box 15, Folder 15)
      - Meeting, 1948 (Box 15, Folder 16)
        Report of Exec. Sec., Nov. 20-21, 1948
      - Meetings, Jan.- May. 1948 (Box 15, Folder 17)
      - Meetings, June-Dec. 1948 (Box 15, Folder 18)
      - Correspondence, June 1949 (Box 15, Folder 19)
      - January 1949 (Box 15, Folder 20)
      - Feb.-Aug. 1949 (Box 15, Folder 21)
      - Meeting, May 13-14, 1949 (Box 15, Folder 22)
      - Meeting, Sept. 16-17, 1949 (Box 15, Folder 23)
        Materials and notes.
      - Alfred E. Smith Award, 1959 (Box 15, Folder 24)
      - Board Materials, 1950 (Box 15, Folder 25)
        Correspondence report of the field worker, 1950
      - Sick leave, 1951 (Box 15, Folder 26)
      - Meeting and Correspondence, Jan. 1951 (Box 15, Folder 27)
        Includes Dec. 1950 meetings
      - Meeting and Correspondence, Feb. 1951 (Box 15, Folder 28)
      - Meeting and Correspondence, August 1951 (Box 15, Folder 29)
      - Meeting and Correspondence, Sept. 1951 (Box 15, Folder 30)
    - Sub-Series b: House of Delegates
      - Code of Ethics, 1926-1927 (Box 15, Folder 31)
      - Code of Ethics 1926-1927 (Box 15, Folder 32)
      - Code of Ethics Comm. report, 1928 (Box 15, Folder 33)
      - General, 1929 (Box 15, Folder 34)
      - Code of Ethics, 1930-1931 (Box 15, Folder 35)
      - Code of Ethics, 1930-11931, 1930-1931 (Box 15, Folder 36)
      - Meeting, list of delegates, 1939 (Box 15, Folder 37)
      - General, 1947 (Box 15, Folder 38)
      - Banquet-100th Anniversary, 1945 (Box 15, Folder 39)
      - Meeting, Nov. 1946 (Box 15, Folder 40)
        Resolution Comm. report and other material
      - General, 1948-1949 (Box 15, Folder 41)
        some material on ethical procedure and tenure, 1948-1949
      - General, 1948-1949 (Box 15, Folder 42)
      - Minutes of Meetings, 1950 (Box 15, Folder 43)
        1950 Preliminary report on Code of ethics
      - General, 1950 (Box 15, Folder 44)
      - Joint code of Ethics, 1950 (Box 15, Folder 45)
        (School Ed. Members teachers), 1950
      - General, 1950 (Box 15, Folder 46)
    - Sub-Series c: General Subject Files
      - Correspondence- General, 1935 (Box 15, Folder 47)
      - Exec. Secretary's retirement resolution, 1935 (Box 15, Folder 48)
      - Correspondence, 1935-1953 (Box 15, Folder 49)
        General, 1935-53
      - Revision in the organization of NYSTA, 1936 (Box 15, Folder 50)
      - Mabel Simpson-past president, NYSTA, 1938 (Box 15, Folder 51)
      - Committee on Equitable Assessments of NYSTA report, 1939-1940 (Box 15, Folder 52)
      - Buffalo Teachers Fed. Meeting, Oct. 30, 1940 (Box 15, Folder 53)
      - Joint Classroom Teachers Committee Exec. Subcommittee meeting, 1940 (Box 15, Folder 54)
        May 25,1940
      - Correspondence-General, 1940-1950 (Box 15, Folder 55)
      - Report of the Director of Studies of NYSTA, 1940-1941 (Box 15, Folder 56)
        (five years of fact-finding) - Arvid Burke 1940- 1941
      - Correspondence-General, 1941 (Box 15, Folder 57)
      - Constitutional revision-correspondence, etc., 1941 (Box 15, Folder 58)
      - Proposed Budget, 1942-1943 (Box 15, Folder 59)
      - Zone Presidents Meeting, April 17, 1943 (Box 15, Folder 60)
      - Correspondence, 1944-1948 (Box 15, Folder 61)
      - Correspondence-General, 1946 (Box 15, Folder 62)
      - Constitutional Revision Committee, 1947-52, 1947-1952 (Box 15, Folder 63)
      - Board of Directors recommendation to NEA Exec. Comm., 1948 (Box 15, Folder 64)
      - Report of Classroom Teachers Comm., 1948 (Box 15, Folder 65)
      - Correspondence re: Constitution, 1948 (Box 15, Folder 66)
      - Correspondence re: Planning Comm., 1948-49, 1948-1949 (Box 15, Folder 67)
      - Association platform, 1949 (Box 15, Folder 68)
      - Committee Report of Committee to study size of House of Delegates, 1949 (Box 15, Folder 69)
      - Proposed NYSTA Employees Retirement Plan, 1949 (Box 15, Folder 70)
      - Sliver Bay Workshop materials, 1949 (Box 15, Folder 71)
      - Classroom Teacher council minutes, 1953 (Box 15, Folder 72)
      - Committee Reports, 1955 (Box 15, Folder 73)
      - Assessment Committee Report, n.d. (Box 15, Folder 74)
      - Design for Association Seal by Miss Weeks (Box 15, Folder 75)
      - Resolutions (Box 15, Folder 76)
      - Committee on Zone Structure, Organization and Representation (Box 15, Folder 77)
      - Miscellaneous Documents (Box 15, Folder 78)
  - Sub-Series C: Goold Subject Files, 1950-1971, 1950-1971
    G. Howard Goold was Executive Secretary from 1951-70. This series contains Goold's files on the various NYSTA committees. The files contain committee reports to the Board of Directors, correspondence of Goold's re: those committees, memoranda and minutes. The files are arranged alphabetically by key word and chronologically within a particular committee. Due to the frequent name changes and office jargon used to refer to those committees, the folders are crossed indexed.
    - Sub-Series a: Committees
      - Committees (Box 16, Folder 2)
        General materials
      - Committee on Accidental Death Insurance for retired members, 1966 (Box 16, Folder 3)
        Contains general memos plus one memo describing developments in the search for insurance for retired members, 1966.
      - Council for Administrative Leadership 1959-1965 (Box 16, Folder 4)
      - Committee on Advancement of American Citizenship (Box 16, Folder 5)
        Contains progress reports, general correspondence, leaflets on the subject of citizenship, a summary of the Sept. 16th meeting, the platform and resolutions of NEA (June 28- July 3, 1953), and the report of the Senate Subcommittee to investigate the administration of the Internal Security Act and other Internal Security Laws dealing with the subversive influence in the educational process, 1953.
      - Committee on Advancement of American Citizenship, 1954 (Box 16, Folder 6)
        Contains a committee progress report, committee minutes 9Jan. 14, 1955) and a report to the House of Delegates (Nov. 22, 1954). Also correspondence of the committee President Fred Ambellum.
      - Council of Affiliates, 1961-62, 1961-1962 (Box 16, Folder 7)
      - Council of Affiliates, #2, 1961-62, 1961-1962 (Box 16, Folder 8)
      - Council of Affiliates, Minutes, Nov. 11, 1963 & April 19, 1963 (Box 16, Folder 9)
      - Affiliation Review Committee, 1962 (Box 16, Folder 10)
      - All Zones Executive Committee - General correspondence,1957 (Box 16, Folder 11)
      - Study of American University Professors Plan Committee, 1962 (Box 16, Folder 12)
      - Association, Organization and Structure Committee contains the committee's report for 1963-1964 (Box 16, Folder 13)
        see also: Committee on Organization and Structure
      - Bylaws Committee, 1963-1966 (Box 16, Folder 14)
        (Delegate Election) contains committee reports for 1963 and 1965-66 dealing with delegate nomination procedures and resolution procedures.
      - com. In re to Candidate for the Retirement Board, 1966 (Box 16, Folder 15)
        Contains guidelines for the selection of candidates for a member of the retirement board of NYSTRS and correspondence announcing the candidacies of August Horstman Muriel H. Weber for the position on NYSTRS, 1966.
      - Special Board Planning Committee for Centennial Celebration of Free Public School Act., 1966 (Box 16, Folder 16)
        Contains a memo to the Bd. Of Dir. On suggested activities for the State Assn., and the classroom. Also background material on the Free School Law of 1967 and school attendance (1865-1870), 1966.
      - Committee to Study Division of the Central Western Zone, 1966 (Box 16, Folder 17)
        Contains the report to the Bd. Of Dir. And various data on which the committee's report was based, 1966.
      - Chapters Committee to Study Proceedings of House of Delegates, 1966 (Box 16, Folder 18)
        Contains the report of the committee, replies to a House of Delegate questionnaire, and various drafts of report, 1966.
      - Chapters Committee to Study Proceedings of House of Delegates, 1966 (Box 16, Folder 19)
      - Citizenship Committee, 1957 (Box 16, Folder 20)
        Contains the committee reports to the Bd. Of Directors, minutes of the first meetings (June 8, 1957) and general correspondence, 1957.
      - Classroom Teachers Committee, 1953 (Box 16, Folder 21)
        General correspondence, 1953.
      - Classroom Teachers Committee Meeting, 1953 (Box 16, Folder 22)
        February 20-21, 1953.
      - Classroom Teachers Committee, 1954 (Box 16, Folder 23)